           location  ...   daily_d1
date                 ...           
2021-06-20    India  ...  3048024.0
2021-06-21    India  ...  8203530.0
2021-06-22    India  ...  5841374.0
2021-06-23    India  ...  3134333.0
2021-06-24    India  ...  5931674.0

[5 rows x 7 columns]
           location vaccine  ... daily_d1  projected_d1
2021-12-27      NaN     NaN  ...      NaN  1.030362e+09
2021-12-28      NaN     NaN  ...      NaN  1.034570e+09
2021-12-29      NaN     NaN  ...      NaN  1.038778e+09
2021-12-30      NaN     NaN  ...      NaN  1.042986e+09
2021-12-31      NaN     NaN  ...      NaN  1.047194e+09

[5 rows x 8 columns]
India COVID Vaccination Summary until 24 June 2021
Vaccinated 247,652,194 out of 1,000,000,000 with only single dose.
Need 752,347,806 in 190 days until 31 December 2021 @ 3,959,725 per day.
Current vaccination rate (last 10 days average): 4,208,115 per day.
May get only 1,047,194,044 and will trail by -47,194,044.
May reach target population by 20 December 2021 at this rate.
Namaskar, I made my first video on COVID vaccination trend in India on 29 May more as a need of the hour that I felt from within to perceive and then mathematically analyse the situation of vaccination in our country myself and share the views with others. Subsequently I wrote a story on Medium.com a week later to follow that up with some revised and more practical figures. I have provided the links to both of the efforts in the description. Please go through them if you are interested.
https://youtu.be/JomMd0nvm2k
https://parijatprasun.medium.com/covid-vaccination-in-india-are-we-on-track-8198c5e516c9
It has been almost a month since the video was published and in this one month the scenario has changed a lot, which is, for a change, pretty positive. In this story we'll try to assess the emerged situation.
First of all, let's pay attention to a very special day in this said period, 21 June, which is International Yoga Day. And what is the connection of International Yoga Day with the course of COVID vaccination? I don't know. Nevertheless, that was the special day that was chosen to bring up some long-awaited changes in the country's vaccination policy and that's the reason this day has become significant for us in this assessment.
On 21 June India recorded a humungous number of 8,203,530 vaccinations of only first dose administered in a single day. This is definitely an achievement, and a moment of pride and hope for every single one of us beyond doubt.
We saw celebratory statements and posts everywhere, which is not bad. No wonder some of the statements became haughty disregarding facts. I have complete faith in the Co-WIN system judging by its overall operational design and transparency observed so far. Our whole analysis is based on data from Co-WIN dashboard, so there is no scope of doubt about the correctness of the figures, at least till now. Surprisingly, the Co-WIN dashboard itself shows some abnormal figures in the days preceding the special day with respect to some specific states in India which will certainly raise a few questions in the minds of people who rely on information rather than perception about how such a high number could be achieved in a single day. Anyway, let's not get into that discussion. On the whole, we are quite happy about the numbers because at the end of the day, it's for our own benefit.
While writing this story the number of vaccinated people with at least one dose till 24 June 2021 is 247,652,194, increased by about 68,479,246 since the last count in my follow-up story published on 6 June that was 179,172,948.
<Show plot 1>
Based on the revision I incorporated in my follow-up story, the current rate of vaccination (CVR) as of now is 4,208,115 which is calculated taking an average of last 10 days' counts. During my story it was around 2,566,157.
<Show plot 2>
This Manhattan plot shows the drastic increase in the rate thanks to the International Yoga Day accomplishment that is standing tall like the statue of unity amongst other high-rises.
The analogy with cricket is inevitable. On one hand, we can see the asking rate or required vaccination rate (RVR) has in fact gone up from 3,931,919 in my story to 3,959,725, but on the other hand, the encouraging thing is that the CVR is currently higher than the RVR! Yay! At this rate we will not only complete vaccinatation of our target figure of 1,000,000,000 people, we will do it by 20 December 2021 well within our target date. And by 31 December 2021 we'll be able to surpass the target and reach around 1,047,194,044. Bravo!, or rather Bravi! The more the better. The sooner the better.
<show plot3>
Now we have to ensure that we have enough supply and proper distribution of vaccines so we can maintain this rate in the coming days. We'd rather be ravenously hopeful that there will be a few more special days like the last one in a short time. We'll now have to think of administering the second dose as well within the shortest time possible. We're all rooting for that, badly, because the number of people with full vaccination is still lurking around only 52,401,833. This is being deprived of the importance it deserves. Because 'No one is safe, until everyone is.' Thanks for reading.
I'd love to hear from you about your thoughts, feelings, views on this topic through your claps, likes, and comments at the following places -
twitter.com/parijatprasun
facebook.com/parijatprasun
